<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<channel>
<title>LandChad.net: Web Guides for Internet Landchads!</title>
<description>Tutorials on minimalist webpage creation and server maintenance.</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<link>https://landchad.net/rss.xml</link>
<atom:link href="https://landchad.net/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<image>
<title>LandChad.net Web Guides for Internet LandChads</title>
<url>https://landchad.net/pix/chad.gif</url>
<link>https://landchad.net/rss.xml</link>
</image>

<!-- LB -->

<item>
<title>Hosting Your Own Git Repositories &ndash; LandChad.net</title>
<guid>https://lukesmith.xyz/git.html</guid>
<link>https://lukesmith.xyz/git.html</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 07:19:51 -0400</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
    <header><h1>Hosting Your Own Git Repositories</h1></header>
    
    <main>
        <img class=titleimg src="pix/git.svg">
        <p>
        Once you have your own VPS or other Internet-available server, you can
        start hosting your own git repositories. The goal of this tutorial is
        for you to go from</p>
        <pre><code>git clone github.com/...</code></pre>
        <p>to</p>
        <pre><code>git clone YourLandChadDomainName.xyz/...</code></pre>
        <p>
        so you can cultivate your own homegrown, grass-fed code, rather than
        relying on a centralized proprietary service like GitHub.
        </p>
        <h2>Installing git</h2>
        <p>
        You most likely already have it installed on your server, but if not,
        run:</p>
        <pre><code>apt install git</code></pre>
        <p>
        We don't need any additional software, <code>git</code> itself ships
        with everything needed to host a remote repository!
        </p>
        <h2>Creating bare repositories</h2>
        <p>
        For each repository you want to host, you will need to manually create
        what's called a "bare" repository on your server. These hold all the
        commits and any other git data needed for your repository, but without
        an expanded "index" in which you can just browse all the files of a
        certain commit in the file system.
        </p>
        <p>
        These repositories need to be owned by the <code>git</code> user, and
        you should probably pick a directory where you will store them all. One
        sane choice is under <code>/srv/git/</code>, and we will use this as the
        example directory for the rest of the tutorial, but any other path will
        do as well.
        </p>
        <h3>Become the git user and create the directory</h3>
        <p>
        If you're logged in to your server as root and have <code>git</code>
        installed, you can become the <code>git</code> user by executing
        </p>
        <pre><code>su git</code></pre>
        <p>
        Now navigate to/create your desired directory, for example
        </p>
        <pre><code>cd /srv
mkdir git</code></pre>
        <h3>Create the repo</h3>
        <p>
        Now you can create the bare repository with
        </p>
        <pre><code>git init --bare my-repo.git</code></pre>
        <p>
        By convention, bare repository names end with ".git".
        </p>
        <p>
        Repeat the above command for any other repositories you want to host.
        </p>
        <h2>Syncing local repositories with your server</h2>
        <h3>Set up SSH login for the git user</h3>
        <p>
        You will need to be able to login remotely via <code>ssh</code> as the
        <code>git</code> user we've used before. To do this, you will either
        need to set up a password for the <code>git</code> user by running
        <code>passwd git</code>,
        or copy your public SSH key from your local machine to
        <code>/home/git/.ssh/authorized_keys</code>.
        See the <a href="sshkeys.html">SSH keys instructional</a> for details
        (just log in as <code>git</code> instead of <code>root</code>).
        </p>
        <h3>Syncing a new repository with your server</h3>
        <p>
        If you've just created a new repository on your local machine, you will
        need to tell <code>git</code> where the remote repository is to be able
        to sync with it (using commands like <code>git push</code> or
        <code>git pull</code>). We do this by defining a "remote" for your
        repository.
        </p>
        <p>
        A remote is just a named URL remembered in your repo's configuration. So
        we need a name and a URL. By convention, the "main" remote is called
        "origin". The URL has the format <code>user@host:path</code>, where:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <code>user</code> is <code>git</code>, the <code>git</code> user
            we've already worked with before.
          </li>
          <li>
            <code>host</code> is your domain name.
            Alternatively you could even use your server's raw IP address.
          </li>
          <li>
            <code>path</code> is the absolute path to the repository on the
            server, in our example <code>/srv/git/my-repo.git</code>
          </li>
        </ul>
        </p>
        <p>
        So, to create a new remote, run:
        </p>
        <pre><code>git remote add origin git@yourdomain.xyz:/srv/git/my-repo.git</code></pre>
        <p>
        Now you'll be able to run <code>git push origin master</code> to push
        your commits or <code>git pull origin</code> to pull from the remote.
        </p>
        <h3>Syncing an existing repository</h3>
        <p>
        If you've already set up your local repository to sync with a service
        like GitHub it probably already has a remote called "origin". You can
        see your repo's remotes with:
        </p>
        <pre><code>git remote -v</code></pre>
        <p>
        You can follow the above instructions, substituting an arbitrary other
        name other than "origin" to create a differently named remote, e.g.
        </p>
        <pre><code>git remote add vps git@...</code></pre>
        <p>
        Now you'll be able to push/pull with <code>git push vps master</code>
        and <code>git pull vps</code>, respectively.
        </p>
        <p>
        Or, to completely sever ties with your centralized git provider, first
        remove the original origin with:
        <code>git remote remove origin</code>
        and then follow the instructions as above.
        </p>
        <h2>Contribution</h2>
        <ul>
            <li>Martin Chrzanowski -- <a
                href="https://m-chrzan.xyz">website</a>, <a href="https://m-chrzan.xyz/crypto.html">donate</a></li>
        </ul>
    </main>
	
]]></description>
</item>


<item>
<title>Requiring Passwords for Webpages (HTTP Authentication) &ndash; LandChad.net</title>
<guid>https://lukesmith.xyz/auth.html</guid>
<link>https://lukesmith.xyz/auth.html</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 07:19:27 -0400</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
    <header><h1>Requiring Passwords for Webpages</h1></header>
    
    <main>
        <img class=titleimg src="pix/auth.svg" alt="access control with nginx"/>
        <p>HTTP basic authentication will allow you to secure parts (or all) of your website with a username and password without the trouble of PHP or Javascript.
        This will work with any Nginx server.
        </p>
        <h2>Installation</h2>
        <p>We will be using the command <code>htpasswd</code> to make username and password pairs.</p>
        <pre><code>apt install apache2-utils</code></pre>
        <aside>
            <p>The apache utils has a small username-password pair encryption tool.</p>
            <p>Like the other on this site, this tutorial is for Nginx, <strong>not</strong> for Apache servers.</p>
        </aside>
        <p>
        Now think of a username and password and remember them.
        </p>
        <pre><code>htpasswd -c /etc/nginx/<strong>myusers</strong> <strong>username</strong></code></pre>
        <aside>
            <p>The <code>-c</code> flag creates a file. You can make the path of this file anywhere outside of your webroot.</p>
            <p>Obviously the username is up to you as well.</p>
        </aside>
        <p>
        Type out your password twice to confirm. You can do this as many times as you'd like.
        </p>
        <p>Check out user name password pairs (the password will be securely hashed):</p>
        <pre><code>cat /etc/nginx/<strong>myusers</strong></code></pre>
        <h2>Nginx Config and Auth Basic</h2>
        <p>
        From here, we are going to edit our websites config file in <code>/etc/nginx/sites-enabled</code>.
        Have in mind which folder you'd like to secure. Add something like this:
        </p>
        <pre><code>server {
    #...
    location /<strong>secret-folder </strong> {
        auth_basic "What's the Password?" ;
        auth_basic_user_file /etc/nginx/<strong>myusers</strong> ;
    }
    #...
}</code></pre>
        <aside>
            <h4>Huh?</h4>
            <p>If you're stuck, try finding the line <code>location / {</code></p>
            <p>Just below this block is where you should add the custom location block</p>
        </aside>
        <p>If you'd like to do the opposite, such as making the entire site private except for a public section, do this:</p>
        <pre><code>server {
    #...
    auth_basic "What's the Password?" ;
    auth_basic_user_file /etc/nginx/<strong>myusers</strong> ;
    location /<strong>public</strong>/ {
        #...
        auth_basic off ;
    }
    #...
}</code></pre>
        <h3>IP Addresses</h3>
        <p>If passwords aren't enough we can ban an ip or accept one.</p>
        <pre><code>location /api {
    #...
    allow 192.168.1.23:8080 ;
    deny 127.0.0.1 ;
}</code></pre>
        <p>If you want to check both a username and password with an ip address, use the <code>satisfy</code> directive.</p>
        <pre><code>location /api {
    #...
    satify all ;
    allow 192.168.1.23:8080 ;
    deny 127.0.0.1 ;
    auth_basic "What's the Password?" ;
    auth_basic_user_file /etc/nginx/<strong>myusers</strong> ;
}</code></pre>
        <h3>Complete Example</h3>
        <pre><code>http {
    server {
        listen 80;
        root /var/www/website ;
        #...
        location /<strong>secret-folder</strong> {
            satisfy all ;
            allow 192.168.1.3/24;
            deny 127.0.0.1 ;
            auth_basic "What's the Password?" ;
            auth_basic_user_file /etc/nginx/<strong>myusers</strong> ;
        }
    }
}</code></pre>
        <p>
        Now check your configuration with <code>nginx -t</code>
        </p>
        <p>Reload nginx and you're good to go!</p>
        <strong>Contributor</strong>  -  <a href="https://tomfasano.xyz" target="_blank">tomfasano.xyz</a>
    </main>
	
]]></description>
</item>


<item>
<title>Cronjobs &ndash; LandChad.net</title>
<guid>https://lukesmith.xyz/cron.html</guid>
<link>https://lukesmith.xyz/cron.html</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 07:19:04 -0400</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
    <header><h1>Using Cronjobs to run scheduled tasks</h1></header>
    
    <main>
        <p>
        Cron is a service that lets you run scheduled tasks. These tasks are called <strong> cronjobs. </strong> If you have already followed the initial course you will have already used cron when you set up certbot.
        </p>
        <h2> What tasks would I want to schedule? </h2>
        <p>
        You can schedule anything! Some examples of what you might have done already include:
        <ul>
            <li> <code> updatedb </code> to update your <code> locate </code> database </li>
            <li> <code> certbot </code> to update renewing of your https certs </li>
        </ul>
        Some tasks that you might <em>want</em> to schedule may include:
        <ul>
            <li> Package updates - if you really just want to leave your server alone you can automated updating packages on your server </li>
            <li> Backups - you may want to backup certain files every day and some every week, this is possible with cron </li>
        </ul>
            <p>
            And many more, anything you can do can be turned into a cronjob.
            </p>
            <h2>Basic Cronjobs</h2>
            <p>
            This the preferred method for personal tasks and scripts, it's also the easiest to get started with. Run the command <code> crontab -e </code> to access your users crontab
            </p>
            <p>
            Once you have figured out the command you want to run you need to figure out how often you want to run it and when. I am going to schedule my system updates once a week on at 3:30 AM on a Monday.
            </p>
            <p>
            We now have to convert this time (Every Monday at 3:30 AM) into a cron time. Cron uses a simple but effective way of scheduling when to run things.
            </p>
            <p>
            Crontab expressions look like this <code> * * * * * command-to-run </code>
            The five elements before the command tell when the command is supposed to be run automatically.
            <p>
            So for our Monday at 3:30AM job we would do the following:
            <p>
            <pre><code> .---------------- minute (0 - 59)
 | .------------- hour (0 - 23)
 | | .---------- day of month (1 - 31)
 | | | .------- month (1 - 12
 | | | | .---- day of week (0 - 6)
 | | | | |
 * * * * *
30 3 * * 1 apt -y update && apt -y dist-upgrade</code></pre>
            <h3>Some notes</h3>
            <ul>
                <li>On the day of the week option, Sunday is 0 and counting up from there, Saturday will be 6.</li>
                <li><code>*</code> designates "everything". Our command above has a <code>*</code> in the day of month and month columns. This means it will run regardless of the day of the month or month.</li>
                <li>The hour option uses 24 hour time. 3 = 3AM, while use 15 for 3PM.</li>
            </ul>
            <h3>More examples</h3>
            <p>
            Let's add another job, our backup job (for the purposes of this our backup command is just called <code> backup</code>) We want to run <code> backup </code> Every evening at 11PM, once we work out the timings for this we can add the to the same file as the above by running <code> crontab -e </code> This would mean our full crontab would look like this:
            <pre><code>0 23 * * * backup</code></pre>
            <h3>Consecutive times</h3>
            <p>
            Suppose we want a command to run every weekday.
            We know we can put <code>1</code> (Monday), but we can also use <code>1-5</code>
            to signify from day 1 (Monday) to day 5 (Friday).
            </p>
            <pre><code>0 6 * * 1-5 echo "Wakey, wakey, wagie!" >> /home/wagie/alarm</code></pre>
            <p>The above <code>echo</code> command runs every Monday through Friday at 6:00AM.</p>
            <h3>Non-consecutive times</h3>
            <p>
            We can also randomly specify non-consecutive arguments with a comma.
            Suppose you have a script you want to run at the midday of the 1st, 15th, and 20th day of every month.
            You can specify that my putting <code>1,15,20</code> for the day of the month argument:
            </p>
            <pre><code>0 12 1,15,20 * * /usr/bin/pay_bills_script</code></pre>
            <h3>"Every X minutes/days/months"</h3>
            <p>We can also easily run a command very several minutes or months, without specifying the specific times:
            </p>
            <pre><code>*/15 * * * * updatedb</code></pre>
            <p>
            This cronjob will run the <code>updatedb</code> command every 15 minutes.
            </p>
            <h3>Beware of this Rookie Mistake Though...</h3>
            <p>
            Suppose you want to run a script once every other month.
            You might be <em>tempted</em> write this:
            </p>
            <pre><code>* * * */2 *</code></pre>
            <p>
            That might <em>feel right</em>, but this script <em>will be running once every minute during that every other month</em>.
            You should specify the first two arguments, because with <code>*</code> it will be running every minute and hour!
            </p>
            <pre><code>0 0 1 */2 *</code></pre>
            <p>This makes the command run <em>only</em> at 0:00 (12:00AM) on the first day of every two months, which is what we really want.</p>
            <p>
            Consult the website <a href="https://crontab.guru">crontab.guru</a> for an intuitive and interactive tester of cronjobs.
            </p>
            <h2>User vs. Root Cronjobs</h2>
            <p>
            It is important to note that user accounts all have different cronjobs.
            If you have a user account <code>chad</code> and edit his crontab with <code>crontab -e</code>,
            the commands you add will be run as the <code>chad</code> user, not <code>root</code> or anyone else.
            </p>
            <p>
            Bear in mind that if you need root access to run a particular command,
            you will usually want to add it as root.
            </p>
            <h2>System-wide cron directories</h2>
            <p>
            <code>crontab -e</code> is the typical interface for adding cronjobs, but it's important to at least know that system-wide jobs are often stored in the file directory.
            Some programs which need cronjobs will automatically install them in the following way.
            </p>
            <p>
            Run the command <code> ls /etc/cron* </code> you should see a list of directories and there contents. The directories should be something like the below
            <ul>
                <li> /etc/cron.d  <em> This is a crontab like the ones that you create with </em> <code> crontab -e </code> </li>
                <li> /etc/cron.hourly </li>
                <li> /etc/cron.daily </li>
                <li> /etc/cron.weekly </li>
                <li> /etc/cron.monthly </li>
            </ul>
            <p>
            The directories cron.{hourly,daily,weekly,monthly} are where you can put <strong> scripts </strong> to run at those times. You don't put normal cron entries here. I prefer to use these directories for system wide jobs that don't relate to an individual user.
            </p>
            <h2>Contribution</h2>
            <ul>
                <li>Mark McNally -- <a href="https://mark.mcnally.je">website</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCMiInY8BhSUtCarO6uu6i_g">Youtube</a></li>
                <li>Edits and examples by Luke</li>
            </ul>
    </main>
	
]]></description>
</item>


<item>
<title>Mirror your site over tor</title>
<guid>https://lukesmith.xyz/tor.html</guid>
<link>https://lukesmith.xyz/tor.html</link>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 07:15:39 -0400</pubDate>
<description><![CDATA[
    <header><h1>Mirror Your Site Over Tor</h1></header>

    <main>
        <img class=titleimg src="pix/tor.svg" alt="Tor logo">
        <p>
        Now that you have a website, why not offer it on a private alternative such as the onion network?
        </p>
        <h2>Setting up Tor</h2>
        <h3>Installing Tor</h3>
        <p>Firstly we need to add the tor repo's to have the latest up to date version or tor.</p>
        <pre><code>apt install -y apt-transport-https gpg
echo "deb https://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org buster main
deb-src https://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org buster main" > /etc/apt/sources.list.d/tor.list</code></pre>
	<p>Then we need to add the gpg keys to our keyring</p>
	<pre><code>curl -s https://deb.torproject.org/torproject.org/A3C4F0F979CAA22CDBA8F512EE8CBC9E886DDD89.asc | gpg --import
gpg --export A3C4F0F979CAA22CDBA8F512EE8CBC9E886DDD89 | apt-key add -</code></pre>
	<p>Now update and install tor</p>
	<pre><code>apt update
apt install tor deb.torproject.org-keyring</code></pre>
        <h3>Enabling Tor</h3>
        <p>Then edit the file <code>/etc/tor/torrc</code>, uncommenting the following lines:</p>
        <pre><code>HiddenServiceDir /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/
HiddenServicePort 80 127.0.0.1:80</code></pre>
        <aside>
            <h4>Optional: Running multiple onion services</h4>
            <p>If you want to forward multiple virtual ports for a single onion
            service, just add more HiddenServicePort lines (replace the 80 with any unoccupied port).
            </p>
            <p>If you want to run multiple onion services from the same Tor client, just add another
            HiddenServiceDir line.</p>
        </aside>
        <p>Now start and enable tor at boot</p>
        <pre><code> systemctl enable --now tor </code></pre>
        <p>If the next command outputs <q>active</q> in green you're golden!</p>
        <pre><code> systemctl status tor</code></pre>
        <p>Now you're server is on the dark web. The following command will give you your onion address:</p>
        <pre><code> cat /var/lib/tor/hidden_service/hostname</code></pre>
        <h2>Adding the Nginx Config</h2>
        <p>
        From here, the steps are almost identical to setting up a normal website configuration file.
        Follow the steps as if you were making a new website on the webserver
        <a href="nginx.html">tutorial</a> up until the server block of code. Instead, paste this:
        </p>
        <pre><code>        server {
            listen 127.0.0.1:80 ;
            root /var/www/<strong>landchad</strong> ;
            index index.html ;
            server_name <strong>your-onion-address</strong>.onion ;
        }</code></pre>
        <aside>
            <h4>Clarification</h4>
            <p>Nginx will listen on port 80 for your <em>server's</em> localhost.</p>
            <p>The <code>root</code> line is the path to whichever website of yours you'd like to mirror.</p>
        </aside>
        <p>
        From here we are almost done, all we have to do is enable the site and reload nginx which is also covered in <a href="nginx.html#enable">the webserver tutorial</a>.
        </p>
        <h3>Update regularly!</h3>
        <p>Make sure to update Tor on a regular basis by running:</p>
        <pre><code>apt update
apt install tor</code></pre>
        <p><strong>Contributor</strong>  -  <a href="https://tomfasano.xyz" target="_blank">tomfasano.xyz</a></p>
    </main>

]]></description>
</item>


<item>
	<title>Cryptocurrency Tutorials Completed</title>
	<guid>https://landchad.net/index.html#crypto</guid>
	<link>https://landchad.net/index.html#crypto</link>
	<pubDate> Tue, 29 Jun 2021 08:10:31 -0400</pubDate>
	<description><![CDATA[<p>There is now a set of basic tutorials on cryptocurrency wallets and concepts up.
		The goal here is to allow people to receive tips for sites using all free and open source and peer-to-peer technology.</p>

	<p>More tutorials on crypto management and exchanging may be added later, but these focus simply on basic concepts and setting up wallets. They include:</p>

	<ul>
		<li><a href="https://landchad.net/crypto.html">The Case for Crypto for Normal People</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://landchad.net/bitcoin.html">Accepting Bitcoin</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://landchad.net/monero.html">Accepting Monero</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://landchad.net/openalias.html">Setting up OpenAlias for your site</a></li>
		<li><a href="https://landchad.net/bat.html">Enrolling in the Basic Attention Token project</a></li>
	</ul>]]></description>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Welcome to LandChad.net!</title>
	<guid>https://landchad.net</guid>
	<link>https://landchad.net</link>
	<pubDate> Mon, 28 Jun 2021 08:21:44 -0400</pubDate>
	<description><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to LandChad.net!</p>
<p>This website is for step-by-step tutorials that allow people to host and maintain their own website and other web services on the cheap or free.</p>
<p>There is already a full basic tutorial on website creation on the site <a href="https://landchad.net/index.html#basic">here</a>.
Following the tutorials can take as little as an hour, but will help you set up a VPS, and NginX server and encrypt your new webpage with Certbot.</p>
<p>Next I plan adding general info on HTML and CSS and how to manage a website.</p>
<p>More stuff like running your own email server and more will be added shortly as more articles are finalized.</p>
]]></description>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
